<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the Essex Watchmens watchword, being 63 of them in number. Or a discovery of their ignorance, in denying liberty to tender consciences in religious worship, to be granted alike to all. Also, shewing how persecution for conscience came in. / By Edw. Barber freeman of Engl. citizen &amp; marchant-taylor of London.</title>
            <author>Barber, Edward, d. 1674?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E552_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E561_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205724</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865019</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E552[9] or 86:E561[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the Essex Watchmens watchword, being 63 of them in number. Or a discovery of their ignorance, in denying liberty to tender consciences in religious worship, to be granted alike to all. Also, shewing how persecution for conscience came in. / By Edw. Barber freeman of Engl. citizen &amp; marchant-taylor of London.</title>
                  <author>Barber, Edward, d. 1674?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copies: "Aprill 30 1649"; "June 23 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165214:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>An Anſwer to the ESSEX</hi> Watchmens Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, <hi>being</hi> 63 <hi>of them in number. Or a diſcovery of their Ignorance, in denying liberty to tender conſciences in religious worſhip, to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alike to all. Alſo, ſhewing how perſecution for conſcience came in.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 20. 21. 23.</bibl>
               <p>Woe unto them that call evill good and good evill, that put darknes for light, and light for darknes, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter. Woe unto them that are wiſe in their own eyes, and prudent in their owne ſight, which juſtifieth the wicked for reward, and take away the righteouſnes of the righteous from them.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 36,</bibl>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſſe, that every one that is left in thine houſe ſhall come and crouch to him for a peece of ſilver and a morſell of bread. &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10. 11.</bibl>
               <p>His watchmen are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all dumb doggs which cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber; yea, they are greedy doggs which can never have enough. And they are ſheapheards that cannot underſtand, they all look to their own way, every one for his gane from his quarter.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 30. 31.</bibl>
               <p>A wonderfull and filthy thing is committed in the Land, The Prophets Propheſie lies, and the Prieſts receive gifts in their hands, and my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple delight therein, What will ye then do in the end thereof?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 1. 2.</bibl>
               <p>Woe he unto the Paſtors that deſtroy, and ſcatter the ſheep of my Paſtour ſaith the Lord. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the Paſtors that feed my people, ye have ſcattered my flock, and driven them away, and have not viſited them. Behold, I will viſit upon you the evill of your doing ſaith the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 8. 12.</bibl>
               <p>I have written unto him the great things of my Law, but they were counted as a ſtrange thing.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſ. 9. 7. 8.</bibl>
               <p>The daies of viſitation are come, the daies of recompence are come, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall know it, the Prophet is a foole, the ſpirituall man is mad; for the multitude of thine iniquity, and the great hatred. The Watchmen of <hi>Ephraim</hi> was with my God, but the Prophet is the ſnare of a Fowler in all his waies and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Houſe of God. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 3. 4. Why doſt thou ſhew me iniquity, and cauſe me to behold grievances? &amp;c</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 2. 3. 4.</bibl>
               <p>Son of man, prophecy againſt the Shepheards of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord God unto the Shepheards, woe be to the Shepheard of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that do feed themſelves, ſhould not the Shepheards feed the flocks. Ye eate the fat and you cloath you with the wooll, ye kill them that are fed, but ye feed not the flock. The deſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthned, neither have ye healed that which was ſicke, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ye brought again that which was driven away, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By Edw. Barber <hi>Freeman of</hi> Engl. <hi>Citizen &amp; Marchant-Taylor of London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:165214:2"/>
            <p> FOr as much, as the Author holdeth forth all due obedience unto juſt authority, who are Gods Miniſters, to take vengeance one them that do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, As alſo, the diſtinct Office of the ſervants of Chriſt in the free faith, and full diſpenſation of the Goſpel, without forcing the conſcience by humane Compulſion; For Magiſtrates ought not to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, but to protect all thoſe who live under their authority, that they may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlines and honeſty. And, for that the Author produceth moſt pregnant Scriptures, to prove and illuſtrate ſuch Truths as are contained in this Treatiſe; all which, tend to the confirmation and conſolation of all thoſe who love the Truth in ſincerity; therefore I doe ſay.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill the</hi> 2, 1649.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
               <signed>Theodore Jennings,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165214:2"/>
            <head>To thoſe pretended VVatchmen of ESSEX in generall, and in perticular to all ſuch, as love the publiſhing of that glorious Everlaſting Goſpell of KING JESUS in ſincerety.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur condition being like the ſtate of <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the Craftſ-men, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 24. to the 29. Your Eſtates, Tithes, Honour, yea your all-being not onely in great danger, I cannot blame you to cry out for help, your <hi>Diana</hi> and her Magnificence and Temple, being likely, not only to be deſpiſed &amp; deſtroyed; but your craft alſo being in great dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger to be ſet at naught. And alſo your cunning craftines whereby you lie in waite to deceive, diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding, I cannot but admire at your weaknes in that you take upon you the name, or title of the Miniſters of the Goſpell, having received ordination from your reverend Fathers, the Lord Arch-Biſhops, and Lord Biſhops, &amp;c. pretending to renounce that Ordination ſent over by <hi>Auſtine</hi> the Monke, from Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. <hi>Peters</hi> pretended Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and Chriſts Vicar Generall upon earth; but this being diſcovered, &amp; your craft failing herein <hi>Jure divino,</hi> you obtaine an Ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament <hi>Jure humano</hi> to ordaine withall, making good the proverb, <hi>a bad ſhift is better then none at all,</hi> by which meanes you became Parliaments ſervants, and not Chriſts Miniſters, from whom alſo you know you have your wages by their Ordinance with trebble damages, and upon ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all commitment without Bayle or mainprize, being in your eſteeme better then Chriſts words, <hi>freely you have received, freely give, Matt.</hi> 10. 8. or the Apoſtles <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 33. 34. 35. compare with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 11, 12. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 2. 9. &amp; 2. 3. 8. or as <hi>Fox</hi> in his <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments</hi> declares, <hi>The maintenance of the Miniſters is the pure almes of the Church.</hi> A condition to meane, and low for theſe pluſh and ſilken Miniſters of theſe times.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165214:3"/>
            <p> And truly, as you came in, and began to be ſet up by the Sword, and authority of the civill Magiſtrate: even ſo you ſtand and continue; and not by any rule, power, or Authority of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And for the wounding the Goſpell through your ſides which you ſpeak of, if you conſider, and weigh your words in the Ballance of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, you will find it to be your ſelves that cheifly wound it, as your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceſſors the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> did the Doctrin of the Apoſtles, as <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 1. to the 21. and 6. 8. to the 14. and 22. 22. from whence <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> ſweetly obſerves, <hi>That falſe Teachers, becauſe they will not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, flee from diſputations to Magiſtrates, and open ſlandering, and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; and that the firſt bloudy perſecution of the Church of Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and ſprung from a Councell of Preiſts by the ſuggeſtions of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity Doctors.</hi> But your words hold true, concerning the true Miniſters of the Goſpell, who can prove their call, and Ordination by the word of God, as <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 27. 33. 34. 35. 36. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23, to the 28.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay, you are charged to the Authors of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms troubles, fomenters of theſe unnaturall diviſions; and bloudy wars, who are they whoſe eyes the Lord in any meaſure hath opened but ſee it? Who have been the main Inſtruments but you? The one part of you ſtiring up the King &amp; his pary, the other part of you the Parliament &amp; their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to fight &amp; kill one another for the Goſpell, though brethren and in the neareſt relation in Church fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>How did you preſſe that text <hi>curſe ye Meroz, yea with a bitter curſe,</hi> to cauſe people to bring in their plate, money and jewells; and to ſend out their husbands, ſervants and children, and if they died in the cauſe, their ſoules would be in heaven, before their bodies would be in the graves? And how did you diſſemble, to ſtir up men to go out againſt the Kings Army, and yet not againſt the King and to bring [all men] without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons to condigne puniſhment, yet not the King? But when you ſaw your honour, riches, &amp; indeed [your all] was lapt up in him, then with <hi>Pilate</hi> you began to change your notes, &amp; to pretend to waſh your hands in Innocency ſaying, <hi>I am clear from the bloud of this juſt man; But be not deceived, God is not mocked, for whatſoever a man ſoweth that ſhall he reap. And as you have ſowen in bloud, ſo ſhall ye have blood to drink for ye are worthy.</hi> Yea the whole Antichriſtian State, from the Prelate to the Sexton, as well as from the Pope to the pooreſt Fryer; becauſe in you, to wit, in that State is found the blood of Prophets and Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth; all which, all thoſe whoſe eyes the Lord
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165214:3"/> hath in any meaſure inlightned, knowes you have in your meaſure fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that for your own meere Intereſts, power, and gaine of your goodly fat benefices (which now are) as <hi>Demetrius</hi> with the Tradeſmen of the like occupation was, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 24 to 30. In great danger and hazard of loſing, which ſome had rather have the ruine of the Nation, then the loſſe of their Trade, gaine, and benefice; for are you not ſuch as <hi>Micha</hi> ſpeaks of that preach for hire, <hi>and divine for money, and yet will leane on the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus you whoſe names are there ſubſcribed are proved, although Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> yet no Miniſters of Chriſt, but State Miniſters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot act according to the example of the Apoſtles, or other the faithfull Servants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> till ſuch time as with the Jewes. <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 19. yee repent and be converted that your ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, and untill ſuch time as you change your mindes, and obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> againſt whom, in his Members you have ingaged to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your own pride, covetouſneſſe, and perſecution, with contempt of your poor brethren whom you ignorantly pretend, to be miſled with ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and falſe zeale, but brethren I hope that through ignorance you do it.</p>
            <p>To the next, you have not without great weakneſſe diſcovered your ignorance, that when God according to his promiſe is inlightning the earth with knowledge, as the waters cover the Sea, in diſcovering the myſterie of Iniquity, and throwing down the Kingdom of Antichriſt, whereby your Church indeed is in great danger and hazard, [but not the Church of Chriſt] which by this meanes flouriſheth abundantly, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing dayly, And therefore there muſt be great alterations in Doctrine and Worſhip, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 13. <hi>Every plant which my heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted up.</hi> And for yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r faithfull conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious Profeſſors as you call them, to be perſecuted to bonds, flight, and impriſonment, Its well your eyes are opened in your own cauſe, to ſee perſecution for Conſcience ſo great a ſinne which all this while you have wincked at, [it ſeemes the caſe is altered] had you formerly made Chriſts rule yours: whatſoever you would that men ſhould do unto you, the ſame do you unto them, this need not have been:</p>
            <p>And truly Sirs, if Popery ſhould not be connived at, what would become of all your adminiſtrations. And for your grievous op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in the Liberties and properties of the Subjects, which you ſay
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165214:4"/> you fighed for [good Sirs pitty your ſelves, or be better informed for the greateſt burthen that ever came of late to this Land, was that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Tithes with treble dammages, or commitment without bayle or main prize upon non payment.</p>
            <p>For the Parliaments Declaration you ſpeak of, upon the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time of meeting apprehending the danger of the State and the Church, how it ſay upon your hearts, it may eaſily be conceived, the day approaching their Declarations, Petitions, Remonſtrances, &amp;c. The blame lying upon the evill Councellors, but who were thoſe evill Councellors, ſearch and ſee, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 20. 21. who muſt perſwade <hi>Ahab</hi> to go up and fall at <hi>Ramouth Giliad,</hi> but the evill ſpirit in the mouth of all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: here you may clearly ſee the chief Inſtruments and Inſendiaries, compared with <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. 13. 14.</p>
            <p>Here was the cauſe of fear, and the Kings leaving the Parliament, and rayſing his Army, which kindled that fire which will hardly be quenched, but in the diſtruction of you or the Kingdom, if not timely prevented. And for the League and Covenant you ſo much ſpeak of, we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire but the performance thereof, and in particular, for Religion to have it eſtabliſhed according to the word of God, and the beſt reformed Churches, which I hope you will grant to be according to the primitive inſtitutions; for know through the mercy of God, we are not ignorant, that your National Presbyterial Churches are as truly Antichriſtian, as the Papal or Prelatical, it being the third part of that great City <hi>Babylon, Revel.</hi> 16. 19. <hi>which now comes in remembrance before God to give unto her the cup of the fierſneſs of his wrath,</hi> compared with verſe 13. 14.</p>
            <p>And as the Kings of the earth have given their power and ſtrength unto the beaſt, as in the raiſing, ſo to the upholding of that Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtate, they therein giving their power and ſtrength unto the beaſt, making Warre, with the Lambe in his Members, to wit, with his poor Saints and Servants: But the Lambe ſhall overcome them, for he is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. 13. 14. <hi>And they that are with him, are called, and choſen and faithful,</hi> compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>But the waters where the whore ſitteth, are peoples and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, and nations and tongues, not redeemed and gathered out from them, and ſo made Kings and Priests, being redeemed by his blood, out of every kindred and tongue, and people and Nation.</hi> Revel. 5. 9.</p>
            <p>Alſo obſerve, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. 16. <hi>Theſe ten hornes there ſpoken of, which are ten Kings,</hi> to wit, Chriſtian Kings as you call them, who ſhall upon the conſideration of their being ſo wofully bewitched by thoſe Froggs and Locuſts that come out of the ſmoke, that aſſendeth out of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165214:4"/> pit, hate the whore and make her deſolate &amp; naked, &amp; eate her fleſh, &amp; burn her with fire, for God hath put into their hearts to fulfil his wil, and to agree, and give their Kingdom to the beaſt, untill the words of God ſhall be fulfilled. And truly we may now ſay as Chriſt once ſaid, Luke 4. 21. <hi>This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your eares.</hi> That therefore the Magiſtrate would conſider this, and take notice that for your part you are not the men that the Lord will give deliverance to his people by, but according to the words of the Lord by <hi>Jer.</hi> the 49, 20. Surely the leaſt of the flock ſhall draw them out, ſurely a company of poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed Mechanick men muſt doe it.</p>
            <p>Again, Conſider how much Innocent and Ignorant blood hath been ſpilt by the civill Magiſtrates, to ſet up and uphold, not theirs, but the Kingdom of Antichriſt, leaſt it be one day made good according to the ſaying of <hi>Iſaiah, Iſa.</hi> 60. 12. For that Kingdom and nation that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh, yea thoſe nations ſhall be utterly waſted, of which cup of Gods wrath, this Kingdom with ſome others have already deeply taſted, according to <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 17, 18. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 23. And he beheld them and ſaid what is this then that is written, the ſtone which the builders rejected, the ſame is become the head of the corner, whoſoever ſhall fall on that ſtone ſhall be broken, but on whomſoever it ſhall fall it will grind him to powder. You being ſuch indeed as <hi>Micha</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Micha</hi> 3. 5. Thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets, that make my people erre, that bite with their teeth and cry peace, and he that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare warre againſt them, &amp;c. compared with, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. 2 3, 4.</p>
            <p>Next you ſay, The Parliament ſeeing which way the Councel of the King ſteered, apprehended a neceſſitie of raiſing armes for the defence of themſelves and the Kingdom, wherein they make you their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ſtirre up the people (as fitteſt for that purpoſe) wherein they declare for the maintaining of the Proteſtant Religion, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you have ſate ſo long, and enjoyed ſo many goodly fat benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by their favour, yet have you never declared to the people, what this Proteſtant Religion, ſo called, and which you ſo much ſpeak of is, much leſſe proved your Presbyterian Nationall Church and Directorie to be it. And Sir I hope you think the preſervation of the Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe ſervants they are, and you ought to be, but are indeed grown their Maſters, according to <hi>Salomons</hi> words, being indeed that evill which he ſaw under the Sun, Eccleſ. 10. 5, 6, 7. <hi>There is an evill</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165214:5"/> 
               <hi>which</hi> I <hi>have ſeen under the ſun, as an error which proceedeth from the Ruler. Folly is ſet in great dignity or height, and the rich ſit in low place. I have ſeen ſervants upon horſes, and Princes walking as ſervants upon the earth.</hi> I ſay I hope you will have them preferre the good and ſafety of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before any particular perſons whatſoever. But had you been Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, you would have done as they, did mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 1. to the 4. who refuſed to leave the word of God to ſerve Tables.</p>
            <p>And truly for ingaging in the cauſe, being called unto it by lawfull Authority, in matters civill I grant they are a lawfull Authority; But in matters Eccleſiaſticall concerning the government of the Church of Chriſt, there [neither they] nor you have any authority, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being wholly on Chriſts ſhouldiers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6. compare with <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 18. <hi>James</hi> 4. 12. he ruling by his own Lawes, and not your acts nor commands.</p>
            <p>And truly had it been, that you had been Miniſters of the Goſpel, you durſt not leave your flock to attend upon the Civill State and affairs of the Kingdom, ſeeing the Apoſtles thought it not meet to leave the word to ſerve Tables, that was to look to the neceſſity of the Saints; for which ſervice they choſe out ſeaven Deacons, fitly qualified for that purpoſe as before is ſhewed. I ſhall ſay no more to this, but what the Lord ſaith <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 7. to the 17. And for powring out your prayers in your daies of humiliation, you have done as the Lord complains <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 2. to the 8. <hi>Yet they ſeek me dayly, and delight to know my waies, as a Nation that did righteouſnes, and forſook not the Ordinance of their God: they aske of me the Ordinance of Juſtice: they take delight in approaching to God. Wherefore have we faſted ſay they, and thou ſeeſt not? Wherefore have we afflicted our ſoul, and thou takeſt no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your faſt you finde pleaſure, and exact all your labours. Behold, ye faſt for ſtrife, and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickednes, ye ſhall not faſt as ye do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high. Is it ſuch a faſt that I have choſen? a day for a man to afflict his ſoul? is it to bow downe his head like a Bulruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him? wilt thou call this a faſt, and an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable day to the Lord? Is not this the faſt that I have choſen to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to undoe the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free; and that ye break every yoake? Is it not to deal thy bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out to thy houſe? when thou ſeeſt the naked that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165214:5"/> own fleſh, then ſhall thy light break forth as the morning, and thy health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily, and thy righteouſneſſe ſhall go before thee. The glory of the Lord ſhall be thy rearward, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For your Appeale to God the ſearcher of all hearts, to whom you muſt give accompt of all your ways, that theſe were your grounds of your firſt Engagement and intentions in it, But pray take in with you the love of money the root of all evill.</p>
            <p>And for your amazement, conſider what the Lord ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 9. 10. Stay your ſelves and wonder, they are blind and make you blind, they are drunken, but not with wine, they ſtagger, but not with ſtrong drink, for the Lord hath powred out upon you the ſpirit of deep ſleep, and hath cloſed your eyes, the Prophets and your rulers, the ſeers hath he covered <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again you ſay, to ſee a warre begun for the defence of Religion, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to end in the ruin thereof, herein you diſcover your great ignorance in the myſtery of the Goſpel, for now is the Lord making good his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that the earth ſhall be filled with the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea. God powring out his ſpirit upon all fleſh, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 4. Where they all ſpake as the ſpirit gave them utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance [not Books, &amp; Arts, Learned at the Univerſities.] And this is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deſire of that faithfull ſervant and type of Chriſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> when <hi>Joſhuah</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun</hi> his ſervant, deſired <hi>Moſes</hi> to forbid <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> from propheſying, ſaying: Envieſt thou for my ſake, would God that all the Lords people were prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpirit upon them, for know the Miniſters of the Goſpel are fitted for their ſervice by gifts from heaven, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 8. 11. to the 15. And not by Arts, learned at <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge;</hi> although I deſire not in the leaſt to take any thing from them, that is properly due to humane learning, as thereby to fit men for the ſervice of the State and Common Wealth.</p>
            <p>Again you ſay, the Warre was begun for the defence of the King and Parliament, to end in the death of the King, and violation of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Herein you ſhew as little judgement in civill things as in ſpirituall, but your <hi>London</hi> brethren at <hi>Zion</hi> Colledge hath been ſufficiently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this,</p>
            <p>Next you ſpeak of the feares about Religion and Parliament, which you ſay is turned into ſorrows, I blame you not, for the myſterie of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is diſcovered, and your cunning craftineſſe whereby you lye in wait to deceive alſo, who are thoſe great merchants of the earth, with your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165214:6"/> weeping and wailing, for no man buyeth your merchandize any more? The which is much aggravated in you by the Agreement of the people, wherein your flattering with the Parliament, concerning the tender ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is much diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And for the draught of poyſon you ſpeak of, I wiſh this nation had been no more poyſoned with the golden cup of the Whore; And for the love &amp; care you ſpeak of, to the people of your reſpective flocks, your Ordinance for Tyths with treble damages without bayle or mainprize, upon refuſall will ſufficiently demonſtrate it, wherein you have as your reverend Fathers indeavoured, to rule with violence, not by love.</p>
            <p>And whereas your hearts tremble, to think of the ſubverſion of the ancient well grounded government of the Kingdom; the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, what do you meane? what ayle you? Have not your ſelves done this, in cutting of your Reverend Fathers the Prelates? Alaſſe! they by their Agreement deſire to take away all ſlaverie and tyrannie, brought in by Tyrants, and their flatterers, in their Civill or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Government, and inſtead thereof inright the Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> and their poſterity in their civill rights; and the liberty of the Goſpel of King Jeſus in its due, to wit, to ſet up his government by his lawes and Statutes only.</p>
            <p>Next you ſpeak of an unlimited power of Parliament, and that in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſurely the word of the Lord is fulfilled, <hi>Iſay</hi> 44. 25. Saying that fruſtrateth the tokens of Lyars, that maketh diviners mad, that turneth wiſemen backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſhneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But truly Sirs, I cannot agree with you in neither of theſe, for firſt in civill things, for which they are properly called together, they are not to act for their own ends, and by reſpects, but for the good, ſafety, and wel being of the people, their Truſters or Impowrers, by whom they may, and ought to be called to an account, if they ſhould neglect to performe their duty: For if in things civill, the Parliament have an unlimited power, why complain you of the Executions done in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes by a Parliamentarie power, with the conſent of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers the Prelates. As alſo in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes upon <hi>Barrow, Greenwood</hi> and <hi>Penrie,</hi> who were hanged for profeſſing againſt the Common Prayer book, which now you practice, the caſe being alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, neither are we ignorant of the turnings, changings and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, of you Prieſts, as in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights dayes Papiſts, in <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. Proteſtants, in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Papiſts, in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165214:6"/> in K. <hi>James</hi> and K. <hi>Charles</hi> his dayes, for the Biſhops and Epiſcopal Government. Now for the Presbyterian, a greater Benefice being a load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone ſufficient to carrie the greater part of you after it, like ſome Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers that looks more at the greatneſſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fee, then the goodneſſe of the cauſe, nay being Feed, leaves his Client, and turns on the other ſide, I would there were none ſuch fate in the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For Religion, they receive no authority or charge from God, he having given that power and prerogative onely to his Sonne King Jeſus, they being Maſters of the fleſh only, but God the Father of Spirits, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is worſhip being ſpirituall, he requires only vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, ſpirituall worſhippers to worſhip him, as <hi>John</hi> 4. 24. <hi>God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the many Oaths, Proteſtations, and Covenants you ſpeak of, I feare, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>For theſe the Land mourneth,</hi> for it had been good if they had been fully debated concerning the lawfulneſſe of them, before they had been with ſuch violence forced upon the Nation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though now you deſire not to have them kept: for if not lawfull by the word of God, they are of no more force then theirs that had bound themſelves with an Oath, neither to eate nor drink, till they had killed <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 23. 12.</p>
            <p>And whereas you object againſt the Ambiguity or darkneſſe, in that it is ſaid, it is intended that Chriſtian Religion ſhould be held forth, as the publick profeſſion of this Nation; yet doth not declare what that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is. And can you object this? Have you forgot the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, Covenant, Vowes, League and Covenant you engaged this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in, for the Proteſtant Religion, yet never did declare what that Proteſtant Religion was you intended, and ſo much ſpake of.</p>
            <p>And whereas you alledge, that all Sects and Errors in the Church of Chriſt (nay take the Church of Antichriſt to it) ſince the Apoſtles dayes, do all lay claime to Chriſtian Religion, and may by this Agreement plead, at leaſt ſtand as Probationers for the priviledge of publick profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: I wonder elſe, how could you all this while come in for a ſhare, and are you not herein as thoſe of whom the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Yee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that ye know God, yet in works you deny him, &amp;c.</hi> Titus 1. 16.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſeem to take offence, that only the Popiſh and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall are left out, I ſhall deſire to include them alſo, otherwiſe I nor you, nor they can obey Chriſts commands, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 12. and <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 31. to wit, <hi>to doe to all men, as we would they ſhould doe unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165214:7"/>
            <p> In the next place, I joy that you deſire that God would increaſe that care in you and others to have Religion reformed to the greateſt puritie in doctrine, worſhip and Diſcipline, according to the word of God, and for inſtructing people in a publick way. And for the confutation of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and Errour, &amp;c. How can this be done, and not liberty of conſcience granted? I hope then the truth will not be confined as it hitherto hath been by you, within the Lips only of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> as you call them. But that others ſhall have liberty to ſpeak, either to add unto, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict if erroneous.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond branch, where ſound doctrine, and a good converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be the only meanes to winne upon the contrary minded, I ſhall plentifully prove that to be according to the Goſpel rule. As 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24. 25, 26.</p>
            <p>And <hi>the ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle towards all men, apt to teach, patient, in meekneſſe, inſtructing the contrarie minded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for your diſtinction of Paganiſme, I have elſewhere, proved your ſtate Antichriſtian, and to be farre worſe, and is compared to <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the vety worſt of Heathens, and therefore not to have given their hands and Seales to Chriſt, nor taken upon them the profeſſion of faith in him, unleſſe it be implicite, to beleeve as the Church beleeves, or by tradition of men.</p>
            <p>And whereas you conceive there is ſo much zeale for God and for his truth in the people of <hi>England,</hi> that did they but know the liberty intended and endeavonred after, they would be ſo far from ſubſcribing their hands to the Agreement, that at the very hearing of it, they would Rent their cloaths, and caſt duſt upon their heads. Sirs I beleeve it, for as the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had been a long time in bondage and ſlavery in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> God ſending his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> to deliver them in their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they murmered againſt him, deſiring rather to return and remain by their Fleſh-pots with Onions and Leekes, then to be tranſported into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo theſe having drunk ſo deep a draught of the golden cup of the Whore from your hands, that they are now in the ſame condition that the Jewes were to whom <hi>Paul</hi> preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Acts</hi> 22. 22, 23. Who ſaid, <hi>Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth for it is not fit that he ſhould live, crying out caſting of their cloaths, and thron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duſt into the ayre, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then you fall into the old ſtrain of enveighing againſt <hi>Anabaptiſts, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians, Arminians, Arians, Socinians, Phocinians, &amp;c.</hi> never ſhewing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165214:7"/> what they are, much leſſe confuting their doctrine to be erronious, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you bring any part of the Goſpell to prove, that theſe men, were they as erroneous as you pretend, ſhould be perſecuted for their opinions, and not enjoy the Liberty of their Conſcience. But herein you ſhew your ſelves brethren to <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John, That would have had fire come down from heaven to conſume the Samaritanes.</hi> But as Chriſt ſaid to them, ſo ſay I to you, <hi>Yee know not of what ſpirit ye are of, for the Sonne of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for your feare of overthrowing the Oath of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premecie, your <hi>Shibboleths,</hi> if they had never been; but according to <hi>James</hi> his words, yea Chriſt himſelf not to have ſworn at all, we had been far better, and the ſin of perjury and ſwearing would not have lain upon the Land, as I feare it now doth.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the diſcourſe is as much as in you lyes to hinder a generall Libertie of Conſcience in matters of worſhip, which is your Parenthiſis, your flie in the box of oyutment, diſabling the power of the civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and Societies in private Families.</p>
            <p>And why are you ſo invictive againſt the Papiſts and Prelaticall, your late reverend Fathers from whom you had your Ordination, being, and maintenance, [Oh Ingratitude!] That children ſhould ſo degenerate, as to ſeek the death and overthrow of their Fathers, that ſo they may get into their poſſeſſions, which you have done by Papiſts and Prelates. And whereas you ſay, Poperie and Prelacie may have liberty by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, becauſe they make profeſſion of faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, do you Presbyters any more? Are ye not of thoſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, Titus 1. 16. <hi>That profeſſe they know God but in works they deny him, being abominable, and diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate, or void of judgement.</hi> In which your practice, you ſhew your woolviſh nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from your Fathers, that notwithſtanding by the providence of God your rage is ſtopt, and teeth ſtruck out. Yet like a muzled Woolfe doe you not retaine your nature of ſnapping and ſnarling, making good the word of the Lord, Jer. 13. 23. <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his skin, on the Leopard his ſpots, then may ye alſo do good that are accuſtomed to do evill.</hi> compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 22. and <hi>chapt.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
            <p>For your concluſion, upon your being better informed and inlightned in your minds, I wiſh your light prove not darkneſſe, for then how great is that darkneſſe, and whereas you do all freely and ſolemnly underwrite the ſubſtance of what is there publiſhed concerning the honour of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165214:8"/> God, I ſhall be of your mind, when I ſee you with the Jewes and the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lor cry out, <hi>What ſhall we doe to be ſaved,</hi> Acts 2. 37. and 16. 30.</p>
            <p>Or with thoſe that uſed curious Arts, and burnt their books, when you go and do likewiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Or according to Chriſts command, and the Apoſtles rule and practice preach the Goſpel freely, getting that Ordinance for Tiths repealed, with your tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble dammages or impriſonment, without Bayle or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price.</p>
            <p>When with the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mzell, in whom was the ſpirit of divination, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 16. You confeſſe thoſe whom you revile and perſecute, to be the ſervants of the living God, that ſhew forth the glorious Inſtitutions of the Goſpel of Chriſt the way of ſalvation, renouncing all Antichriſtian practice and traditions of men, that you have neither precept nor exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for. Then and not untill then, ſhall I judge you to be no Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants againſt Chriſt, nor Sectaries, nor Schiſmaticks from the only rule of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But herein Reader take notice of two things: the ſtate of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Church of the Jewes under the Law, from the world, diſtinguiſhed by circumciſion, and the Church of Chriſt under his government in the time of the Goſpel, diſtinguiſhed by baptiſme or dipping.</p>
            <p>That being a Covenant of works made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his carnall or naturall ſeed after the fleſh. The other being a new Covenant made with Chriſt, beleevers, <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his ſpirituall ſeed, being of the faith of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Gal. 3. 7. 26. 28, 29. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 7. 8. Iohn 1. 12, 13. and 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We hinder not men from Inſtructing, Catechiſing, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their families, either Magiſtrates, or private perſons, yea and to powre out themſelves with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> in prayer for them: But not to uſe any violence or carnall weapons to force them to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that God requires, under the Goſpel by Chriſt, it being ſpirituall, according to that great Charter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. His Churches being ſo gathered in the Primitive times, and ought to be ſo gathered after the Apoſtacie of the man of ſin, to wit, by one and the ſame rule and miniſtrie, &amp;c. being taken from the Heathens or Antichriſtians, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you ſeem to make a difference, for the word ſets forth the ſtate of Antichriſt, to be <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the worſt of Heathens, If you will make a difference.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now deſire to ſhew you what was practiſed under the Law, as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165214:8"/> alſo under the Goſpel, concerning Liberty of Conſcience, with the grounds and reaſons for it. And laſtly ſhew you how perſecution for conſcience came in, and was afterwards agrivated to uphold, not the Church of Chriſt, but the ſtate and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch of Antich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, were our Religion as falſe as you our Adverſaries pretend, yet were that no ground to take away our lives, eſtates, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> baniſh us, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down our houſes to make Iakes therof, and hang us on the timber, as ſome of eminency have preached for before authority, I ſpare to name them. I ſay we proving loyall to our Country, though holding errors in our judgements, yet were that no ground for perſecution, as is cleare from Chriſt by the parable of the Tares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. Whereby the Tares muſt needs be underſtood, men profeſſing a falſe Religion, which when ſome would have had them pluckt up, Chriſt declared his mind to the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary, and commanded they ſhould be let alone, and grow with the wheat, untill the harveſt in the world. Although not in the Church, leaſt men undertaking to pluck up the Tares, wanting wiſedom to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, pluck up the wheat in ſtead thereof, as it hath and doth often come to paſſe, according to the words of Chriſt, which ſhews that ſome ſhall be ſo blindly led, and devoted as to kill the Saints, thinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that they do God ſervice, and therefore Chriſt will have the tares let alone with the wheat, untill the harveſt, then who without great ſin can attempt to pluck them up before that time.</p>
            <p>And this doth no way contradict Gods word which ſaith, that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are Gods Miniſters to take vengeance on them that do evill, the tares being ſinners againſt God in falſe Religion; whom he hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be puniſhed with flaming fire at the day of Chriſt, the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing treſpaſſers againſt men, and are juſtly to be puniſhed by the civill Magiſtrate, and herein we give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God the things that are Gods.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord commandeth, that thoſe that are blindly led on in a falſe Religion, and are offended with him for the teaching of the Goſpel, ſhould be let alone, and referreth their puniſhment to the falling into the ditch, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 14. And <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>For we are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in the ſpirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Lord Chriſt reproveth thoſe Diſciples, that would have had fire come down from heaven, and conſume the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that would not receive him, in theſe words, <hi>Ye know not of what Spirit ye are,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:165214:9"/> 
               <hi>for the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave them.</hi> Which ſheweth plainly, that Chriſt would have no man hurt for Religon, yea, though they were refuſers of himſelf. <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 54. 55. 56.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when the Lord Chriſt ſent forth the twelve to preach the Goſpel of the Kingdom; this is the utmoſt that he directed them unto concerning thoſe that ſhould refuſe to hear their words, namely, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 14. 15. <hi>To ſhake off the duſt of their feet for a Teſtimony againſt them,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their further puniſhment to the day of Judgement. This was clear under the Law, where none was compelled to the worſhip of God by the Authority of the Civill Magiſtrate; but as the Lord did perſwade the heart by his Word. And as this was ſo under the Law, much more in the time of the Goſpel, the Body being of Chriſt: as firſt, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Chriſt given to the Apoſtles, where Chriſt ſheweth, though all power in Heaven and Earth was his, yet he only appoints Preaching the Goſpel, for gathering of his Churches throughout the world: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Pauls</hi> words, where he ſaith, <hi>The weapons of our war-fare are not carnall, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down Imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God. Gen.</hi> 9. 27. <hi>Exo.</hi> 35. 5. 21. 22. 23. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 18. 43. 44. 110. 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 19. 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. 5.</p>
            <p>Again the ſame Apoſtle commandeth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24. <hi>That the ſervant of the Lord ſtrive not, but be gentle towards all men, ſuffering the evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing with meeknes the contrary minded,</hi> proving, if God at any time will give them repentance, that they may acknowledge the Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and come to amendment, out of the ſnare of the Devill. Which plainly ſheweth, that repentance muſt be continually waited for, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by violence and perſecution; and that becauſe repentance is the gift of God, and cannot be given by man: and therefore Religion not to be forced or compelled. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 5. 8.</p>
            <p>According to theſe commands the holy Prophets fore-told, That when the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould ceaſe, in matters of worſhip, and the Law of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould be ſet up inſtead thereof, that then the carnall Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons ſhould ceaſe <hi>They ſhall break their Swords into Mattocks, and their Speares into Sythss, Nation ſhall not riſe againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learne War any more;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſhall ſit every man under his vine and under his own fig-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid, for the mouth of the Lord ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſpoken it; There ſhall none hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountaine, for the Earth ſhall be filled with the knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165214:9"/> when Chriſt came, he taught and practied and ſo did his Apoſtles and ſervants: <hi>Behold my ſervant whom I have choſen, my beloved in whom my Soul is well pleaſed; I will put my ſppirit upon him, and he ſhall ſhew Judgement to the</hi> Gentiles; <hi>he ſhall not ſtrive nor crie, neither ſhull any man he are his voice in the ſtreets; a bruiſed Reed ſhall he not break, and ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flax ſhall he not quench, till he ſend forth Judgement unto victory.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing them to be ſo far from perſecuting thoſe that ſhould oppoſe, and not be of their Religion, that when they were perſecuted they ſhould pray, when they were curſed they ſhould bleſſe, leaving the Judgement to God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2, 4. <hi>Micha</hi> 4. 3. 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 18. 19, 20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24, 25, 26. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 14, to the 20.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of all is, They who are now blind, may ſee; They who now reject the Truth, may receive it; They who are now Tares, may become Wheat; They who are now in the ſnare of the Devill, through wicked works, and adverſaries to the Truth, may hereafter come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; They that are now Blaſphemers and perſecutors as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was, may in time become moſt glorious and faithfull witneſſes, as he did; They that are now Idolators as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſomtimes were, may hereafter as they, become true worſhippers of God; They who for the preſent are no people of God in viſſible appearance, nor under mercy, may hereafter become the people of God, obtaining mercy as the Saints have done; for ſome come not till the eleaventh houre, though ſome came at the Firſt, Third, and ſixt houre, yet ſome not till the laſt; which ſhould they be put to death, becauſe they come not with the firſt, they then would be prevented from comming at all. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 3. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 5. 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Matt.</hi> 20. 6.</p>
            <p>It is affirmed by King <hi>James</hi> of famous memory, in his Speech at the Seſſions of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1609. That it is a ſure rule in Devinity, That God never loves to plant his Church with violence and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>Again, in his Apollogy for the oath of Allegiance, <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. ſpeaking of thoſe Papiſts that took the ſaid Oath, ſaith, I gave a good proof for it; that I never intended perſecution for Conſcience cauſe, but only deſired to be ſecured of them for Civill obedience. It was uſually the condition of the Chriſtians to be perſecuted, but not to perſecute. And lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is to ſee the folly of late times, and we cannot but greive at the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of men, who think by humane Inventions, and carnall aide of Lawes, and Statutes, to help God and with worldly power and pomp, to defend
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165214:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165214:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165214:11"/> the Churches of Chriſt; as if he by his own power were not able to do it, and to perform his own will. <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. 52. 53. 54.</p>
            <p>The Church hath formerly bin known, by enduring Miſery and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment; but it is the marke of the Church of Antichriſt, to terrifie others by imprifonments, banniſhments, and perſecutions, boaſting her ſelfe, that ſhe is highly eſteemed in the world, whereas the true Church of Chriſt cannot but be hated of the ſame. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 18. 19. 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
            <p>It was commanded by the Law, If a man met a betrothed Damſell in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ield, and the man force her, he was to die: Then what ſhall thoſe expect that ſhall force the conſcience the ſpouſe of Chriſt? <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 25. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2. 19. 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</p>
            <p>The example of many Nations, both in Scripture, and at this day known, may ſuffice to ſuffer the conſcience free: <hi>Abraham</hi> lived in <hi>Egypt</hi> in <hi>Gerar,</hi> among the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> after with the <hi>Hittites: Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom; Iſaac</hi> in <hi>Gerar, Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> 430. years, after in <hi>Babylon</hi> 30 years; yet never conſtrained in their Religion. Alſo in the daies of our Saviour, how many Religions were there in that famous Empire of <hi>Caſars,</hi> yet not by him perſecuted, or conſtrained to his Religion. <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>It was the Judgement of <hi>Luther,</hi> That the Lawes of the Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate extended no farther then over the bodies &amp; goods, &amp; that which is externall; for over the ſoule, God will have none to rule but himſelf. And therefore, where-ever the civill Magiſtrate undertaketh to ſet laws, for the ſouls and conſciences of men, he uſurpeth that Government and authority to himſelf, which appertaineth only to God. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89. 27. <hi>Iſa</hi> 33. 22. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 9. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3. 16. <hi>James</hi> 4. 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18. 19.</p>
            <p>And therefore we conceive it, the higheſt degree of Antichriſts impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>ſitting in the temple of God as God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4. in giving Laws to the Conſcience, which is Gods Prerogative onely. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27, 4.</p>
            <p>In the building of the Temple, there was no ſound of Iron heard, to ſhew, that Chriſt will have in his Church a free conſent, not compelled mor conſtained by Lawes and Statutes, for the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their glory unto it. 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 7. <hi>Joſhuah</hi> 8. 31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 24.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Churches of Chriſt muſt look for ſuffering, with every particular member thereof, as he himſelf did, who is their head, being thereby made perfect, being the way and means that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165214:11"/> to publiſh the Goſpel: which cauſed the Fathers to ſay, The blood of the Martyrs was the Seed of the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Heb</hi> 2. 10.</p>
            <p>Therefore Chriſtians are to be exhorted, not compelled: for he that will not do that whereunto he is exhorted and perſwaded, the Goſpel injoyning, is no true Chriſtian as yet; and they that go not this Goſpel way, to perſwade men by exhortation and Counſell, but ſeek to doe it by conſtraint, ſhew themſelves not Goſpel Teachers but worldly Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles rather, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24.</p>
            <p>For conſider, if an earthly King will take it ſo ill, as ſurely he may at his ſubjects hands to have any equalize themſelves with him or ſubmit to a forraigne power, or to make Lawes for his Subjects to be guided and ruled by; how much more the King of Kings Chriſt Jeſus, by whom alone Kings reign, will he ſuffer himſelf to be diſplaced, and an earthly King placed in his throne. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Pro.</hi> 30. 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18. 19.</p>
            <p>Thus we conceive it is clear, That no man ought to be forced in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Religion, the Goſpel being ſpirituall, and requireth onely, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all worſhippers, like to it ſelf: which cannot be made ſo, but by the Word and Spirit of God, which breatheth where and when it liſteth, and not where and when mens Lawes and Statutes pleaſeth; which may make hypocrites, but not true Chriſtians. <hi>As we ſaid unto you before ſo ſay I unto you again, If any man preach any other Goſpel unto you then that ye have received, let him be accurſed for do I now perſwade men, or God? Or do I ſeek to pleaſe men? for if I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt</hi> John 4. 24. John 3. 8. 2 Cor. 5. 10. Gal. 1. 9. 10.</p>
            <p>And thus as you ſee, perſecution was never taught by Chriſt, nor yet practiſed by his Apoſtles, nor by the Primitive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſtians: ſo afterwards it aroſe, and was brought in by the bloody Heathen Tyrants, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by Antichriſt and his Miniſters as appears in <hi>Tho. Beacons Relicks of Rome,</hi> ſet forth with Priviledge <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1563.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Seritius</hi> ordained that Heriticks ſhould be baniſhed, and that no Chriſtian ſhould Communicate with, or keep them company <hi>Anno</hi> 588. <hi>fol.</hi> 214.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> the firſt, not content with the former puniſhment made a Decree, that all Heriticks and Schiſmaticks, with all ſuch as be contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer diſobedient to the holy Church Ordinances, ſhould be put to death by the ſecular power, provided alwaies, that thoſe bloody B. with their Woolf-like Officers, and Antichriſtian adherents, do firſt of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165214:12"/> impriſon and condemn them for Heriticks, and aftewards accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their wicked Decrees, commit them to the ſecular power, and temporall Magiſtrates, as unto their Butchers and Hangmen, to diſpach them out of the way, either by fire, ſword or halter; for theſe holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cry out with their Fore-fathers, and Pope-like Prediceſſors. <hi>Iohn</hi> 18. 31. <hi>It is not lawfull for us to put any man to death. Anno Dom.</hi> 551. <hi>fol.</hi> 215.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3. bearing rule in the year 1215. the Councell of Lattern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was called, or celebrated, where was preſent two Patriarks 70. Arch-Biſhops Metrapolitans, 400 Biſhops 12. Abbots 800. Convinciall Prieſts, the Legates of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, with the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of the Kings of <hi>Spain, Jeruſalem, France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ciprus;</hi> In this Councell it was Decreed, that all Heriticks, and ſo many as do in any point reſiſt the Catholick f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith ſhould be condemned.</p>
            <p>In this Councell was alſo Decreed, that the ſecular power of what degree ſoever they be, ſhould be compelled openly, to ſweare for the defence of the Catholick Faith, And that to the utmoſt of their power, to roote out and deſtroy in their Kingdoms, all ſuch perſons as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th condemned for Herit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cks. And if he do not reform within one whole year, then the Pope is to denounce all his Subjects abſolved, and utterly delivered from ſhewing, or owing any fidelity or obedience unto him, as in this Kingdom it was done by King <hi>Iohr.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that the Pope may give that Land to be occupied, and enjoyed by the Catholicks, and they to poſſeſſe it, all Heriticks being rooted out peaceably, and without contradiction. <hi>fol.</hi> 217.</p>
            <p>Since this anſwer to the Miniſters <hi>Watch-word</hi> was at the Printers, Mr. <hi>John Fereby,</hi> Minſter of <hi>Thoydon Garnon,</hi> one of rhe 63. <hi>Aprill</hi> the 22, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords day, took occaſion much to enveigh againſt Sectaries, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s them.</p>
            <p>But the Author deſires if he doth it out of conſcience, to anſwer him by word in a free diſpute, or by writing, concerning the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Church Ordination, of their Miniſtery, Worſhip, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Maintenance, Baptiſme, or perſecution for conſcience, referring the ſenſure and judgement there of to all judicious hearers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
